foreign
this is March 31st
2023's quarterly Round Table number one
from the active inference Institute
welcome to the active inference
Institute
we're a participatory online Institute
that is communicating learning and
practicing applied active inference you
can find us at the links on this slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us feedback so
we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
today we're going to be checking in with
our regular quarterly Roundtable series
we're gonna first provide some updates
from The Institute scale
then we'll talk about ongoing Education
and Research projects before concluding
with some thoughts on the institute's
paths in the coming year so first
would the two of you like to introduce
yourself I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and also the president of the
Institute
Alex
now yes I uh my name is Alex I'm a vice
president of the Institute and also
an educator and systems thinking
blue please go ahead
hi I'm blue Knight I'm an independent
research consultant in New Mexico and
the secretary for the active inference
Institute
to you Daniel awesome
well let's begin with some
views on the institute at the
organizational scale
first just as a summary overview put us
off to the side
we engage with our Niche and provide
services to it on multiple fronts
here
who we are and what we are is reflected
visually
at The Institute scale
we have several groups including the
ones that we'll be describing in the
coming slides the board of directors the
officers and the scientific Advisory
Board
we have two organizational units
somewhat like departments these
organizational units help support a wide
range of projects related to Education
and Research any general comments that
you'd like to add
yeah let me add
here but yes we're using it's kind of
simple schema but it's actually
represents our
a reason to have this hierarchical
structure explicit and
represent in our
attempts to align with active inference
approach
or organizational side of our activities
so for here we have like connections to
the niche and different scales of
institution in general units projects so
we are like having attention on keeping
a structure alive and see how it's
which affordances it's provide us to
development
as we undergo morphological
and just to give a bit more information
on the governance
the board of directors
serves to implement Institute scale
formal strategy and governance they
specified and provide oversight for the
officers who are closer to the
day-to-day operations at The Institute
and the board of directors applies
active inference at the organizational
scale in contrast and in complement the
scientific Advisory Board assists with a
wide range of tasks to reflect their
diverse backgrounds and approaches so
let's talk a little bit more about the
bod and the Sab
first as to the board of directors are
2022-2023 board of directors are listed
here and we've recently confirmed three
of us here on this stream as the
officers again close to the day-to-day
operations and who one is speaking with
most likely when they email The
Institute
currently we are working towards our
non-profit tax exemption status 501c3
status for our non-profit and we
continue to highlight bolts Dimensions
business operational legal Technical and
social
anything else that either of you would
like to add about our formal
organizational structure
um let me possibly add here but um
uh it's uh on the process of development
it was like needed
legally activities to have all these
people
I mean all these roles for the legal
structure of Institute
and that's great so
great people we have on board
and like from
from the site as I said even having
the like a team of this size
the process and structure is became more
complex
and all such changes took more time to
restructuring
and like for first quarter we started
this process like last year
and even first quarter I will need it to
finalize these activities but it's great
that we
yeah now I mean people
in a rolls and having accordance to
legal requirements and now we can make
next steps possibly we
talk we will take
again out of time but it's kind of new
new form and the speed of such changes
for institute scale is takes more time
thank you it was definitely a memorable
moment when during a scientific Advisory
board meeting one member suggested that
this was stretching the upper limit of
how complex and complicated our
organization should be at our stage and
another contrasted that it was actually
the minimal level of complexity required
to pursue certain legal statuses and so
and another work so we're kind of
straddling that line writing forward
we have the second cohort of our
scientific Advisory Board in full swing
already most have joined meetings are
engaged in other activities we have a
healthy number of returning Advisory
board members and
some great new Advisory board members so
thank you all for your work in the
scientific Advisory Board and we're
looking forward to Bringing forth your
engagements in the coming year in many
many ways anything either of you would
like to add here
uh maybe a dimension about kind of
diversity in terms of people from
different domains and it's growing in a
number of participants
maybe it even looks like
much more people than need it but having
opportunity to discuss
relevant questions for research
different research fields and to have
different insights it's
totally valuable for us and provide us
opportunities to make right steps in
needed directions related to research
site mostly
thank you
there are many ways to engage with the
Institute
there's a lot of asynchronously
available materials like the recordings
of the live streams and other
Productions and the transcripts and so
on things we'll discuss more about and
also for those who want to get more
involved be active in for ants there are
multiple opportunities for action
in the volunteer program by going to our
website and under education finding
volunteer you can support your
engagement with one or as many projects
and activities as you'd like
by registering as a volunteer we'll keep
you in the loop about specific
affordances for your participation for
example registration opening for an
upcoming learning group or some cool new
update with a given project
and for those who are looking for even
more structure we offer an internship
program
we have currently about 10 active
interns from around the world who are
engaging with different research and
education affordances at The Institute
in their own ways reflective of their
own situations the interns engage in
some element of learning and education
usually with textbook groups or other
courses
some element of Project based learning
where they are going to be and are
contributing to different projects
making translations in the ontology or
developing some other kind of work
and the internship has a more active
mentorship and peer facilitation aspect
for whatever your educational and
research Journeys are
any comments on that
we hope that this becomes a very
important Vector for people who want to
catalyze their active inference Journey
we basically cannot imagine a better way
for someone who wants to dedicate one
hour per week 10 hours per week 30 hours
per week whatever it may be we can find
a kind of relationship that's going to
be mutually beneficial
yeah I think it was
quite a smart mutation of our activities
and having that format and having that
actually active people
in game it's the most valuable thing
and having organizing it as flexible as
possible around specific people specific
situation and learning paths
we can keep it
and develop and hopefully it will bring
more people who are interested in
active influence to some actual
activities and learning paths in my
direction
great
with respect to what they call social
media we have our main platforms and
numbers noted here so it's been great to
see continued growth on these fronts
as to the big picture on our activities
the above link
provides a always updated reference
point for the activities that are
ongoing and the times of their meeting
and also links to those documents if you
want to learn more and we're going to go
through many of them today but first
just the 30 000 foot View
these are some of the active activities
at The Institute
all of which are participatory so if
you're curious just wanting to know more
or see a way for you to contribute or
maybe even want to spin up your own
project where you'd be a facilitator we
can talk more about it
ask for learning groups we continue to
have par at all textbook groups
which will be discussed later
we have been active with Sanjeev
namjoshi in the fundamentals of active
inference group working on sanjeev's
book in progress and providing feedback
which
will hopefully be surfaced more and
throughout the year
and also to be addressed later we're
working on category Theory as a learning
group
we organize and produce live streams and
with the transcripts of those live
streams publish an archive
and do other things within language
processing
in active block runs project we're
developing implementations for octave
inference at this point largely using
approaches and codes that are scattered
elsewhere bringing them together and
help making it more coherent for people
who want to engage in active inference
modeling so people who want to engage
with the actual code and see how it
works in a script rather than from a
mathematical or from a philosophical
approach this is a great project to add
into your toolkit
in robotics and embody JF Cloutier
continues to present us with progress on
his work in symbolic active inference
and engage participants in this very
exciting area
in the active inference ontology we
continue to develop translations
definitions examples and counter
examples and methodologies involving the
active inference ontology and how it's
used
and we also have several open hours per
week in our Discord where we have
wide-ranging conversations these are
really great entry points if someone
doesn't even find a specific project
that they're curious about but they just
want to learn more in general
joining any open discussion hour is a
great option because we can field that
conversation then
and just to show a few of our seed or
inactive projects
starting in May we'll have a physics as
information processing course by Chris
Fields we'll talk more about that in a
few minutes
podcast continues to exist albeit a
little bit on the back burner
in software we have several software
ideas and projects that have been
sketched to some extent but are not
engaging regularly to me
as well as the development of Frameworks
for cognitive agent modeling and course
development so we have a good
portfolio for those who choose to engage
with one or more activity
and there are always burners that are on
low or off
let's go into the educational project
updates in the edgio active yeah
organizational yeah
yeah related to education as you can see
now my educational activities became
more and more
important and active and we have
different formats and even on our
planning some creation and our
organization of
education different educational courses
and it's also a result a result of
transformation to Institute when we
consider this
educational function as a specific for
such type of organizations
and for now we kind of I believe is
seeing the results of implementing such
strategies starting to think about
education
and starting to make actions to have
education in place for instance in
Institute
thank you
currently as one of our primary
educational Avenues
we are continuing with our textbook
group centered around the par pazulo and
friston 2022 textbook
so the first cohort has been completed
last year and those who have completed
the cohort are encouraged to join future
cohorts and be participants again or be
learning assistants
the second cohort which began in the
second half of last year is about
two weeks from finishing the whole
textbook and the third cohort which
begun in 2023 is now closing in on
finishing the first half of the tech
support book
uh
uh cohort four will begin with the
beginning of a textbook
in the coming months so check out on our
website the textbook group page if you
want to
register for the fourth cohort or if you
have any other questions
just to summarize it's a really exciting
and inclusive experience to be in the
textbook group people have all
backgrounds different familiarities and
angles of approach to octave inference
everybody has different familiarity with
the active inference ontology and with
equations math statistics philosophy all
these threads that come together in the
textbook group we have fun and we work
together to improve our shared documents
so that we can have a wide variety of
tools and augmented learning approaches
that we wouldn't be able to have a loan
so if you're planning to work on this
textbook at all or if you're curious
about it
there couldn't be a better way to engage
with it
um
moving to another educational project
with a small group of participants we
are working on a category Theory group
this group is an extended dot zero
preparation session for this
draft
dissertation thesis
by Toby Sinclair Smith mathematical
foundations for a compositional account
of the Bayesian brain
and in this group where we have many
different backgrounds and familiarity
with category Theory ranging from
none to some
we are preparing the dot zero background
and context materials for upcoming live
streams with Toby in the middle of 2023
where we're going to be discussing this
incredible work
which brings together in some novel ways
the compositionality of category Theory
with the otherwise non-compositional
Bayesian brain active inference type
approaches we're going to see how it all
works together in the coming years it's
not the end with this dissertation it's
really just the beginning and so it's
been quite exciting to develop
educational materials as a small group
as well as some individuals within the
group developing personal materials like
blogs and syllabus to
help learn at the intersection of active
inference in category Theory
and everyone's welcome to get involved
with this group just as with all the
others and this group is an example or a
template of how we operate deliverable
oriented learning groups at The
Institute
um doesn't mean every person is going to
have homework it just the way that for
example shown here on the right we
structure meetings and set a pace where
we know we could spend five years
working on one page because that's what
the PHD is like but we also move quickly
enough to get things done in reasonable
time frames and have a shared Niche many
pages not shown where we have notes
questions discourse and so on
any
thing blue or Alex on category Theory
maybe not only here but
general for education and courses I
think that we called the value at the
services
for education or course organization
it's kind of unique because it's
evolving and but it's evolving around
some structure and
for ontological work and having it in
place like a ground we can build a lot
of really
valuable valuable services to provide
additional information links connections
between terms ideas questions and so on
and I believe the development and the
direction and trying to apply the same
approach for different educational
activities
um the real brain interesting results
for everyone
awesome agreed
we have recently been very happy to
announce that in May 2023 we will be
hosting a course taught by Chris Fields
physics as information processing you
can find out more in the education
section on our site
it is going to consist of six lectures
live streams by Chris fields and six
live streamed but also participatory
discussion sessions with Andre Aguirre
so you'll be able to access all
materials Preparatory readings
Associated topics recordings of live
streams and so on on this course Coda
and
look forward to learning more about this
it's going to be a great course
anything you want to add
I'm really looking forward to it that's
all I'm super excited I think it's
really like awesome of Chris to put this
forward
um and let us Host this wonderful class
um and yeah we're going to be having
discussions sessions that are um
hopefully transcribed through the active
influence Journal so getting in touch
and participating in these sections is a
good chance to interact with the journal
in that kind of way that's the only
addition I would make maybe yes all the
lectures and discussions and
asynchronously submitted questions and
answers will be compiled and published
and citable so this we expect to be a
multi hundred page
functionally Landmark publication
if you're interested in this area
and you're in this moment in time
do what you can
Alex
ah I just wanted that it's great that we
see with growing connections between
Quantum
Tyrant Quantum information Theory to
active inference
and it's starting to grow and it's bring
us more and more of those principles
into this framework basements so
it's very cool
agreed
we've had a very exciting
2023 for live streams
first just the ask
with your
contributions and assistance we can
co-create a special and engaging
sequence of live streams for the rest of
the year
so everybody listening is welcome to
join you're always welcome to comment
and continue the discussion
also you can join live streams while
they occur you can self-nominate if
you'd like to give a presentation or
have your paper discussed please let us
know or if you have a recommendation or
even a warm introduction that could go a
long way
if you'd like to bring some materials
and perspectives really to the Forefront
you can collaborate on a DOT zero
background and context video
and help lock in the ways that you might
want to share background for a topic to
preempt uncertainty or do any other kind
of service in the epistemic niche and we
meet weekly of course to discuss these
issues just quickly to look at some of
the streams that we've had in this year
2023 so far
um we had guest streams from Adam peace
alireza moderation
Jordan Hall and Matthew Perkowski
Benjamin valendez Baba Brinkman Max Berg
shuji and Vania Visa so these guest
streams ran the gamut from consciousness
to
clinical psychiatric modeling with
active inference improvisation in rap
ecological psychology Civics and
governance physics of creation technical
details on surprise definitions
integration of large language models
with neurosymbolic approaches and formal
ontologies and later today there will be
an orc stream with stray Jane on plural
publics
those are the guest streams and we've
also had a great set of other streams
for paper-oriented live streams
we've had two Series in live stream 52
geometric methods for sampling
optimization inference and adaptive
agents Lance DeCosta joined for both
discussions and has incredible insights
into that group's paper that brings
together the topics in the title and in
the recently concluded 53 sequence on a
pair of papers Snakes and Ladders and
paleoanthropology and to copy or not to
copy in both of these live streams we
had the authors Michael Walker Hector
manrique and Carl fursten joining and
both were very special and illustrative
discussions
we've had two model streams one on Pi
mdp a python package for generative
models of the active inference flavor
that was with Connor Hines and Carl
friston and Tom ringstrom joined for a
presentation reward is not necessary
we also enjoyed a sequence of book
streams and so I'll pass to Blue to say
a little bit more about those book
streams
sure so we have been um going through
this text and discussing the material
presented in the first three parts of
the book and we're not going to do the
um interviews at the end section of the
book just because it's kind of beyond
the scope of what we wanted to cover in
the book streams but we have been going
through week by week chapter by chapter
examining this material which is really
the application of active inference to
governance uh especially like with our
own governance of The Institute like
being forming officers and a board of
directors and how should we factor in
the concept of active inference into our
governance policies so this was a very
interesting group of readings and
discussions that we've had over the last
few weeks and we are going to have a
final discussion coming up in like the
next three-ish weeks hopefully the
author will join us again to discuss the
material but also this discussion we
would really love to have the outside
perspectives for people that have been
engaging this with this material real
either through watching the live streams
or the book streams or have read the
text so if you want to get in on these
discussions of active inference and its
application and governance please get in
touch because we would really like to
have some different perspectives in our
final discussion session
thank you blue and also to Tyler for
this great series
and to kind of
conclude on the live streams and
bring in the journal which is actually
what happens in the work itself
every live stream that we do which can
be found at the code link shown here and
posted in every video description
the slides are available where possible
but also we are developing a utilities
pipeline that automatically downloads
the audio from YouTube uses
artificial intelligence to do speech to
text outputs of markdown and then uses
rendering approaches to render that
markdown and so there's a git folder
where you'll find all the transcripts
and therefore be able to do some
incredible natural language analysis
ontology driven analysis of this Corpus
of several hundred videos and growing
and we look forward to continuing to
improve that pipeline as speech and text
processing Advanced quite rapidly and
techniques and methods that were outside
of our capacity even weeks to months ago
day by day draw nearer so if you'd like
a really open
decentralized science DSi open science
project or Corpus
there are many many ways in the journal
that we can improve the rigor
accessibility and applicability of our
live streams and therefore continue to
add value and meaning
even for live streams from the past
anything to add
all right
so maybe a yes maybe yes
I want the support of that it's gave us
a lot of opportunities to reuse in some
way these transcription from our side is
an Institute Building samples
uh language tools or chats to
communicate about active inference
and
a lot and a lot of opportunities will
arise like next month and
years which is a development of
language models in general is a domain
so we we have like a main piece of for
it a text
and how we will use the
mistakes that how we can what services
we can create which cases we can support
it will be huge and populist people from
community of Institute could share
some ideas how we can improve here and
possibly participate in this project
considering it as a technical heavy
and like
on the frontier of current language
processing tools
thank you Alex indeed to watch all the
videos
may not be possible given limited time
it may not be preferable but to engage
in discourse and synthesize summaries
with
a rich and articulate Corpus where
speakers are also known and we have
connections with the speakers and the
co-authors and all this other kind of
information there are just going to be
many many opportunities so hopefully in
a future Roundtable we can revisit this
go into a little bit more depth and show
the status of our pipeline
such that we can fulfill that vision of
having a live stream and then rapidly
within hours after the live stream have
gotten the audio rendered into markdown
rendered the markdown into a variety of
accessibility
oriented formats it's going to be
amazing
in our last section we'll talk about
some research updates so if you're
watching live please feel free to write
a comment or share favorite memory or do
so in the comments after the video but
we'll go through just a few research
updates and then if anyone has questions
in the live chat address those and then
that'll be it for the Round Table
so just a research overview we have a
handful of ongoing research projects
in the active inference ontology we are
developing the active inference ontology
inactive block prints we are developing
a package that integrates and
facilitates approaches for computational
modeling with active inference and in
robotics and a body Jeff clotcher is
leading the way on some Lego robots that
do symbolic active inference
we have several seed research projects
for those who'd like to for example
explore a graphical interface for active
inference
or look at the broader landscape of
cognitive agent modeling approaches
and lastly
although most
ramified in their manifestations are the
individual research projects so not all
the work that people are engaged in is
necessarily using the documents and the
deliverables of The Institute we also
really honor and want to support the
individual research Journeys that many
are on inside or outside of formal
academic structures and so with our
interns and others who aren't even
interns there are so many exciting
projects that everyone is engaged in
they share during the open hours they
post updates in our Discord and um
we do a lot when we work on our own
projects and group projects
just to give two examples to highlight
um
one of our interns shohei wakayama has
updated his paper on active inference
for autonomous decision making with
contextual multi-arm Bandits and this
has recently been accepted to uh
relevance conference so congratulations
shohei also uh
a variational synthesis of evolutionary
and developmental Dynamics a paper with
both I and blue as co-authors and some
other names that people may find
familiar from the cast of live stream
characters so just a few that we wanted
to draw together but a little bit more
generally
if you have any work that you'd like to
share please let us know and we'll make
sure to highlight it in future
newsletters and roundtables it would be
awesome to have that kind of an update
system so that we could highlight like a
collage or a mosaic of all the works
that people are doing around the
Institute and um it's just been great to
see there are so many others that it was
just hard to pick exactly what ones in
our limited time to put here but we saw
many great developments over the past
month personally and organizationally so
this is just a few of what the research
side looks like
and
in our last minutes
we can talk about whatever
you fellows would like in terms of next
steps or reflections
perhaps Alex first
okay
yeah I think we will continue on uh
structuring and improving activities
related to education
reporting interests from community
and interest for people who are
who can produce educational materials we
will try to support in in all Direction
and provide affordances
on organizational side and possibly on
Communications
and for research
I believe for you we will work on some
kind of research strategy with our
scientific Advisory Board
because for now we have like a few core
research projects ongoing and
it's great Basics we support research of
people who are contacted us
but having in place like a long-term
strategy in research reactions will be a
great achievement if you can present
something related on next round table
related to it
so let's go for my side
thank you Alex blue
so for me I have kind of pulled back if
you're not seeing me around discussing
active inference it's because I have
decided to prioritize building
institutional infrastructure and
institutional capacity for the active
inference Institute so my focus now is
on getting grants for The Institute and
pushing on the 501c3 status
501-3c3 C3 whatever it is the nonprofit
status so um my that's my biggest
priority in focus and I'm looking
forward to kind of getting over a few of
those hurdles and getting back into
um the material because I really do miss
it and I really miss like hanging out
with everyone but I can't I have to like
Focus my attention and effort uh so that
I can continue to focus on active
inference for many years to come
awesome great notes there
indeed the organizational work is
applying active inference
it looks a little different than reading
a paper joining a textbook group
search this quarter has been
um
very rewarding very developmental from
what we can see
it would be extremely helpful and
requested slash appreciated for those
who engaged a lot all the way on down
through a little or not at all
to provide their feedback directly or in
the comments to this video or however
they see fit to let us know about how we
can improve you are our Niche and we act
in first serve for you
having that kind of closure with even
your acknowledgments means a lot and it
does help shape what we can and do offer
on Research Alex I also look forward to
uh what you suggested about developing
more of a research program
so that we can
see where difference things fit and
we're kind of engineering that from the
bottom up but increasingly being able to
take a top-down View
and about education
every textbook group every dot zero
every course is rapidly becoming easier
and easier to organize as we develop
templates expertise and so on and right
now the rate limiting step in those who
want to create or engage with
educational material
is the material itself and so that feels
like a really good step in our active
inference corner of the world prior
there was a lack of content not saying
that there's a sufficient amount now but
hardly any
casual conversations existed and hardly
any technical discussions existed for
especially this Cutting Edge active
inference
developments that truly on a month by
month basis
provide at least new views on older
discussions
and so being able to develop that
material and increasingly support others
who want to teach their own courses like
Chris Fields as well as others that will
be announced and upcoming in the rest of
the year
so those who want to teach or have a
hosted course get in touch those who
want to learn more we hope you're doing
so
and again we appreciate all of the
engagements and feedback it's how we
actually make it happen together
any closing thoughts
just to Express gratitude for everybody
engaging with the Institute keeping us
alive
um and for you guys because you're
awesome to work with and hang out with
it's been fun thank you
thank you officers thank you
participants farewell bye-bye